Finding Aid for Richard A. Ware papers, 1930s-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Richard A. Ware papers 1930s-2005
Ware, Richard A. (Richard Anderson)
0772 Aa 2
11 linear feet
2 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Richard A. Ware (donor no. 9777.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is closed to research until 2035, except for designated family members.
Richard A. Ware was born in New York City, November 7, 1919. He received his B.A. from Lehigh University in 1941 and his Masters in Public Administration from Wayne State University in 1943. Following his graduation from Lehigh, Ware worked as a research assistant with the Detroit Bureau of Government Research, 1941-1942 and personnel technician with the Lend-Lease Administration in Washington, 1942-1943.
After wartime service with the Air Force, Ware worked as research associate to the assistant director of the Citizens Research Council, 1946-1956. During the latter part of these years and for the remainder of his career, Richard Ware served in various capacities with the Earhart and Relm Foundations in Ann Arbor, Michigan, as secretary (1951-1970) and as trustee and president (1970-1984). Thereafter he served as trustee and president emeritus.
During the Nixon Administration, Ware took time off to serve as principal deputy assistant secretary of defense for international security affairs, 1969-1970, then as consultant in the office of the assistant secretary of defense, 1970-1973.
Throughout his career, Ware was active in numerous business, civic, and public policy organizations and groups. He was assistant director of the Michigan Joint Legislative Committee on Reorganization of State Government, 1950-1952 and secretary of the Governor’s Committee to Study Prisons, 1952-1953. Ware was also active in Republican Party activities, particularly during the 1964 presidential campaign of Barry Goldwater when he served as a policy analyst.
The collection is arranged into the following series: Correspondence and speeches; Citizens Research Council, 1946-1956; Michigan Joint Legislative Committee on Reorganization of State Government, 1950-1952; Barry Goldwater presidential campaign, 1964; Earhart and Relm Foundations; US Dept. of Defense, Office of International Security Affairs, 1969-1973; Recollections and analysis of US Dept. of Defense service; Other organizational activities; Various printed, and Videotape.
Subjects:
Ware, Richard A. (Richard Anderson); Earhart Foundation.; Relm Foundation.
- Correspondence and speeches
  - Lifetime Career records volumes
    (include correspondence, memoranda, speeches, and other materials)
    - 1935-1975, 2 volumes (Box 1)
    - 1976-1995, 2 volumes (Box 2)
    - 1996-2005, 1 volumes (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence 1950-1974 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence 1960-1961 (Box 3)
  - Personal correspondence 1970s-1994 (arranged alphabetically)
    - A-K (Box 3)
    - L-Z (Box 4)
  - Speeches 1950-1985 (Box 4)
- Citizens Research Council 1946-1956
  - Articles and miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 4)
- Michigan Joint Legislative Committee on Reorganization of State Government 1950-1952
  - Staff reports, 3 volumes (Box 5)
  - Staff reports, 2 volumes (Box 6)
- Barry Goldwater presidential campaign 1964
  - Notes on the campaign September-November 1964 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence July 30, 1964-July 24, 1965 (Box 6)
  - Draft manuscript by Karl Lamb on the Goldwater campaign staff with comments by RAW, Spring 1965 (Box 6)
  - Collected articles critical of Goldwater's candidacy (Box 6)
  - Master list of scholars willing to be included in advertisement supporting Goldwater (Box 7)
  - Comments by Communist Part members and supporters on the Goldwater campaign (Box 7)
  - Publication: "A report in depth on Barry Goldwater (Box 7)
  - Campaign speeches and press releases (Box 7)
  - Article by Harry Jaffa on Goldwater's acceptance speech 1986 (Box 7)
  - Research and resource materials, correspondence, and memoranda (Box 7)
  - Goldwater campaign speeches (RAW provided resource data), 3 volumes (Box 7)
- Earhart and Relm Foundations
  - Correspondence (including memoranda of RAW to Earhart Foundation) 1986-1994, 5 folders (Box 8)
  - Report of Rehm Foundation (with chapter by RAW (Box 8)
  - Memo from RAW to senior staff member August-September 1983 (Box 8)
- US Dept. of Defense, Office of International Security Affairs 1969-1973
  (security classified documents within this series have been transferred to the vault of the Gerald R. Ford Presidential Library pending their declassification)
  - "Memorandum for the Record" by G. Warren Nutter, Assistant Secretary of Defense, International Security Affairs 1969-1973 (Box 8)
    (drafted by RAW)
  - "The Strategic Potential of Psychological Operations" (July 1970 study prepared at the request of RAW) (Box 8)
  - "Soviet and Chinese Psychological Operations" (July 1970 study prepared at the request of RAW) (Box 8)
  - Photograph album from US-Republic of Korea Defense Ministers' Conference June 02-04, 1969 (Volume 1)
  - Scrapbook January 1969-October 1970 relating to the Nixon administration and to RAW's service in the Defense Department (Volume 2)
  - Office appointment schedule 1969-1970 (Box 9)
  - Memorandum, Terms of Reference for the Proposed Interdepartmental Group for Foreign Affairs Research 1970 (Box 9)
- Recollections and analysis of US Dept. of Defense service
  - Impression of 1st Nixon Administration 1995 (Box 9)
  - G. Warren Nutter Lectures in Political Economy, Thomas Jefferson Foundation Center 1986
    - Reading copy and published copy of "The Pentagon's Office of International Security Affairs 1969-1973 or Two Citizens Go to Washington" (Box 9)
    - Compact disc recordings of the lecture; including comments of the host William J. Baroody, Jr. and introduction of Ware by John F. Lehman, Jr. (Box 9)
    - Compact disc recordings of the remarks made following the lecture at a testimonial dinner for Richard Ware (Box 9)
    - First and second drafts of lecture (Box 9)
    - Letters concerning lecture 1986 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence and other materials relating to an article in Political Science Quarterly regarding the ISA division of the defense department, 1983 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence with Professor Douglas Kinnard his book on the Office of Defense Secretary 1981 (Box 9)
  - Letter to Mrs. G. Warren Nutter commenting on "image problem" at ISA 1983 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence with CIA director William Colby regarding ISA intelligence 1973 (Box 9)
  - Paper by Professor Vincent Davis entitled "The Laird Pentagon 1969-1973; Some Impressions" 1973 (Box 9)
- Other organizational activities
  - Board of Foreign Scholarships (Fulbright), 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Brookings Institute (Box 9)
  - Detroit Mayor's Committee inquiring into policies, practices, procedures Department of Public Welfare 1949 (Box 9)
  - Governmental Research Association 1949-1960 (Box 9)
  - Liberty Fund
    - Miscellaneous correspondence 1960-1994, 4 folders (Box 10)
    - Background and related on "The Rufus Fears Incident", 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Organizational materials (Box 10)
  - Mid-American Fidelity Corp. (Box 10)
  - Mont Pelerin 1986-1992 (Box 10)
  - Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars 1973-1984 (Box 10)
- Various printed
  - Announcements of public administration program at Wayne State University 1946-1950 (Box 11)
    (RAW was field training director)
  - Survey of Wayne County General Hospital 1954 (Box 11)
  - Jail Needs of Wayne County 1955 (Box 11)
  - The Michigan Prison Riots 1953 (Box 11)
  - "We bought an abandoned farm" Detroit Bureau of Governmental Research publication 1941 (Box 11)
  - "A Quarter Century of Citizen Concern with Government" Detroit Bureau of Governmental Research 1941 (Box 11)
  - "Citizen Concern with Government" Citizens Research Council of Michigan 1966 (Box 11)
  - Governmental Research Association 1949-1960 (various titles) (Box 11)
  - Municipal Research Bureaus by Norman H. Gill, 1944 (Box 11)
  - The Government of Cincinnati and Hamilton County 1924 (Box 11)
  - Report of the Michigan Civil Service Study Commission 1936 (Box 11)
  - "All around the town" draft of study of citizen governmental research history and organization by John M. Payne 1960 (Box 11)
  - Vietnamese Realities published by Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Republic of Vietnam 1967 (Box 11)
  - Collected articles regarding conservative/liberal politics and public policy, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Collected articles regarding office of the President (Box 11)
  - "A Proposed Program for the Citizens research Council of Michigan," 1951 (Box 11)
- Videotape
  - "A conversation with Richard Ware" (part of the Liberty Fund "Intellectual Portrait" series), VHS cassette; 1 hr., 42 min. (Box 11)